A Guide to the Personal Papers of Eleanor Lee Templeman, 1928-1990
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Personal Papers of Eleanor Lee Templeman, 1928-1990
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 23
7 boxes.
Templeman, Eleanor Lee Reading, 1906-1990
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Templeman.
Biographical Information
Eleanor Lee Templeman (b.1907-d.1990) grew up in California and lived in Arlington from 1935 until she died. She served as historian of the Society of the Lees of Virginia, and was an active local historian, publishing Arlington Heritage: Vignettes of a Virginia County (1959) and (with Nan Netherton) Northern Virginia Heritage (1966). She contributed many articles to Virginia historical publications, and received awards for her research achievements, including one from Marymount University (1975), and from the American Association for State and Local History (1983).
Scope and Content
RG 23 are papers collected and generated by Eleanor Lee Templeman. The collection measures approximately 3.5 linear feet, and dates from 1928 to 1990, with the bulk of the material falling between 1955 and 1980.
Much of the material in this collection was generated or collected during research for her books, Arlington Heritage and Northern Virginia Heritage. Included are correspondence, notes, clippings and pamphlets. The collection also contains papers reflecting Mrs. Templeman's involvement in civic organizations such as the Arlington Cultural Heritage Commission (1962-1968), the Arlington Historical Commission (1967-1975) and the Arlington Historical Society (1976-1981). There are also copies of some of her articles. A scrapbook of clippings of her newspaper series, "Arlington Heritage," a predecessor of her book, has been copied and can be found in Series 3.
Arrangement
Record Group 23 is arranged in three series. Series 1, Templeman Book Files, comprises research materials for Mrs. Templeman's two books. It is divided into two subseries, Arlington and Other Virginia Locations, each arranged alphabetically by subject. Series 2, Additional Research, the same two subseries and is arranged alphabetically by subject. Series 3, Activities, Events, and Publications, focuses on Templeman's research and work with local historical groups, and is generally arranged alphabetically. Files in Series 3 that contain material about Arlington are marked with (^). Folders containing photographs have an asterisk [*] after the file name. Folders with oversized materials have a double asterisk [**] to denote where material was removed and separation sheets added.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
PG 900, Eleanor Lee Templeman Photograph Collection, consists of Virginia photographs taken or collected by Mrs. Templeman, many of which appear in her books. Similar broad Arlington research collections are RG 76, Personal Papers of Nan Netherton, RG 91, Personal Papers of Dorothea Abbott, and RG 354, C. B. Rose Papers.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Arlington Historical Society; Citizens' associations; Women in community organization; Community organization.; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.); Arlington Heritage: Vignettes of a Virginia County; Northern Virginia Heritage
Contents List
- Templeman Book Files
  - Arlington
    - Abingdon, 1929-1984 (Box 1)
    - Alcova (Box 1)
    - Altha Hall, 1941-1959 (Box 1)
    - Aqueduct Bridge, 1926-1963, 1984-1988 (Box 1)
    - Arlington Archives, 1975-1988 (Box 1)
    - Arlington County Historical Sites Map and Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Arlington Court House and Cornerstone, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Arlington House, 1955-1983 (Box 1)
    - Bailey's Crossroads, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - Ball Spring, 1957-1975 (Box 1)
    - Ballston, 1958-1977 (Box 1)
    - Barcroft (Box 1)
    - Birch and Dittmar, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Boundary Stones, 1957-1969 (Box 1)
    - Brandymore Castle, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Bridges and Canals, 1967-1987 (Box 1)
    - Carlin House, 1944-1959 (Box 1)
    - Carlin Springs, 1967-1976 (Box 1)
    - Demeteries and Other Destroyed Sites (Box 1)
    - Chain Bridge and Doak Mansion, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - Cherrydale, 1922-1958 (Box 1)
    - Churches, 1916, 1952-1959 (Box 1)
    - Clarendon, 1968-1977 (Box 1)
    - Dawson-Bailey House, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Dittmar, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Donaldson-Marcey Records, 1957-1975 (Box 1)
    - Doubleday, 1958-1972 (Box 2)
    - Ellsworth, Colonel, 1961-1970 (Box 2)
    - Febrey (Box 2)
    - Fort Myer, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Fort Strong Villa, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Forts in Arlington, 1957-1967 (Box 2)
    - Forts: Pamphlets: The Defenses of Washington, 1957; The Upper Potomac in the Civil War, 1965; The Symbol and the Sword, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Freedmen's Village, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Glebe House, 1966-1983 (Box 2)
    - Glencarlyn, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Green Valley Manor, 1957-1970 (Box 2)
    - Gulf Branch (Box 2)
    - Hampton Farm (Box 2)
    - Historic Arlington Sites List, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Indians, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Little Tea House 1963 (Box 2)
    - Luna Park, 1906, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Lyon Village, Park (Box 2)
    - Marcey Indenture Copy (Box 2)
    - Marcey Road, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Mills (Box 2)
    - Minor (Box 2)
    - Monuments, Memorials, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Munson Hill, 1957-1962 (Box 2)
    - Phillips and Little Italy, 1926, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Phillips of Minor Hill (Box 2)
    - Potomac Overlook Park and Upton Hill, 1967-1974 (Box 2)
    - Henry Codman Potter, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Prospect Hill (Box 2)
    - Rixey Mansion, 1957, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Roads, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Roberts Lane and Bellevue Forest, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Rosslyn and Rosslyn Marker, 1958-1959, 1982-1988 (Box 3)
    - Saegmuller, Vandenburg, Vanderwerken, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Schools, 1957-1984 (Box 3)
    - Subdivisions and Streets, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Trees, 1966-1976 (Box 3)
    - Trolleys and Railroads, 1957 (Box 3)
    - Virginia Landmarks Commission, 1971-1975 (Box 3)
    - Walker (Box 3)
    - Correspondence about Arlington Heritage, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Arlington Heritage dust-jacket (Box 3)
  - Other Northern Virginia Locations
    - Alexandria, 1959-1967 (Box 3)
    - Annandale, 1958-1962 (Box 3)
    - Burke, Clifton, Fairfax Station, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - Fairfax Miscellaneous, 1921, 1953-1976 (Box 3)
    - Fairfax on Potomac, 1921, 1961-1976 (Box 3)
    - Falls Church, 1959-1972 (Box 3)
    - Fauquier County, 1944-1974 * (Box 3)
    - Fredericksburg, 1967-1970 (Box 3)
    - Leeton Forest, 1933, 1955-1974 (Box 3)
    - Leven Tract, 1917, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    - Loudoun County, 1953, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Loudon County, 1967-1976 * (Box 4)
    - Loudoun County Notes and Pamphlets, 1949, 1958-1975 * (Box 4)
    - Loudoun County Clippings (Box 4)
    - Lyceum, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Maplewood, 1970 (Box 4)
    - McLean - Creat Falls, Madeira Area, 1961-1973 (Box 4)
    - Oak Hill (Fauquier County), 1986 (Box 4)
    - Ossian Hall and Ravensworth, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Prince William County, 1959-1975 (Box 4)
    - Prince William on the Potomac, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Stafford County, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Towlston, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Vienna, Oakton, 1958-1962 (Box 4)
    - Wellington, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Northern Virginia Heritage dust-jacket negatives (Box 4)
    - Endorsements for Northern Virginia Heritage, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Layout Sheets for Northern Virginia Heritage, pages i-30, 1966 ** (Box 4)
    - Layout Sheets for Northern Virginia Heritage, pages 31-80, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Layout Sheets for Northern Virginia Heritage, 1966 (3) (Box 5)
    - Layout Sheets for Northern Virginia Heritage, 1966 (4) (Box 5)
- Additional Research
  - Arlington
    - Analostan Island/Roosevelt Island, 1964-1966 (Box 5)
    - Arlington County, 1959-1976 (Box 5)
    - Arlington County Court House, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Arlington County Seal, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Arlington Memorial Bridge Plaques, 1971-1974 (Box 5)
    - Arlington Song, 1969-1970 (Box 5)
    - Ballston Triangle and Ballston Metro Station, 1970-82 (Box 5)
    - Carlin Springs Road Spelling, 1976-1981 (Box 5)
    - Cherry Valley Park, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Duelling Site, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Kennedy Grave Site, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
    - Map of Historic Data, 1973 ** (Box 5)
    - Marcey Home, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Historical Data, 1932, 1964-1977 (Box 5)
    - Names of Streets, Schools, and Parks, 1969-1974 (Box 5)
    - Nottingham School Building, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
    - Three Sisters Island, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Upton Park, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Vacation Lane, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Other Norhtern Virginia Locations
    - Harper Mansion, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Leesburg, 1970 (Box 5)
- Activities, Events, and Publications
  - Arlington Bicentennial Committee, 1971-1976 ^ (Box 5)
  - Arlington Chamber of Commerce Booklet, 1971-1972 ^ (Box 5)
  - Arlington Cultural Heritage Commission, 1962-1968 ^ (Box 5)
  - Arlington Historical Commission, 1967-1975 ^ (Box 5)
  - Arlington Historical Society, 1976-1982 ^ (Box 5)
  - Frank Ball, 1959-1966 ^ (Box 5)
  - Bicentennial Correspondence, re: Lees of Virginia, 1971-1980 ^ (Box 5)
  - Biographical Material on Eleanor Lee Templeman, 1976-1990 ^ (Box 5)
  - Building Names, 1961, 1973-1975 ^ (Box 5)
  - Civil War Centennial Committee, 1961-1970 (Box 5)
  - Corrections, 1988-1990 (Box 6)
  - Donor Information Copies, 1975-1989 (Box 6)
  - Historic House Association of America, 1983 (Box 6)
  - John Glenn with Eleanor Lee Templeman, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Library Virginia Day, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Marymount Award, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Memorial Day, 1958-1959 ^ (Box 6)
  - Our Town Exhibit, 1956 (Box 6)
  - Pamphlets: House Divided, Legends of Virginia, 1971-1987 (Box 6)
  - Photographs Donated by Eleanor Lee Templeman, Lists, 1972-1983 ^ (Box 6)
  - Rand McNally Corrections, 1981 ^ (Box 6)
  - Time-Life Books, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Trees for Notable Tree Search, 1987-1988 ^ (Box 6)
  - Virginia Counties (Box 6)
  - Virginia Heritage Address Book, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission, 1980 ^ (Box 6)
  - A Visit to Stratford and the Story of the Lees with Corrections, 1977, 1985-1986 (Box 6)
  - Williamsburg Tombstones, 1950 (Box 6)
  - World Day of Prayer Talk, 1961 ^ (Box 6)
  - Eleanor Lee Templeman Achievements and Awards through 1986 (Box 6)
  - Publications of Eleanor Lee Templeman as of 1989 (Box 6)
  - "Articles by Eleanor Lee Templeman, Volume I, Biography and Lee Family," 1928-1989 (1)*^ (Box 6)
  - "Articles by Eleanor Lee Templeman, Volume I, Biography and Lee Family," 1928-1989 (2)^ (Box 6)
  - "Articles by Eleanor Lee Templeman, Volume II, California and Virginia," 1928-1989 (1)^ (Box 6)
  - "Articles by Eleanor Lee Templeman, Volume II, California and Virginia," 1928-1989 (2)^ (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook of Articles from Arlington Heritage, Fairfax Heritage, 1957-1959 ^(1) (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook of Articles from Arlington Heritage, Fairfax Heritage, 1957-1959 ^(2) (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook of Articles from Arlington Heritage, Fairfax Heritage, 1957-1959 ^(3) (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook of Articles from Arlington Heritage, Fairfax Heritage, 1957-1959 ^(4) (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook of Articles from Arlington Heritage, Fairfax Heritage, 1957-1959 ^(5) (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook of Articles from Arlington Heritage, Fairfax Heritage, 1957-1959 ^(6) (Box 7)